"Risks of NAD+ Boosting Supplements"
Most of the reported
side effects
for NAD+ precursors,
like NAM, NR, and NMN,
are relatively rare and minor,
for example, diarrhea,
nausea, rashes, hot flashes,
and leg cramps.
Both NR and NMN
raise NAM levels,
so may share
in the same concerns
regarding sirtuin inhibition,
methyl depletion,
and potential adverse effects
of NAM breakdown products.
Another theoretical concern
of NAD+ boosting
is the exacerbation
of infections
by a group of bacteria
called Haemophilus
(from the Greek
meaning "blood loving,"
though can also cause
infections of the lungs,
brain, throat,
flesh, and joints).
Haemophilus bacteria lack
the ability to make NAD+,
so rely on host levels,
raising the possibility
that higher blood levels
might worsen the disease course
of infected individuals.
Ironically,
elevated NAD+ levels
may also fuel
immune system overreaction
in cases of auto-immune
and inflammatory disease.
When fully activated,
the immune system is voracious.
The immune reaction
to a blood infection
or extensive burns can burn
4,000 calories a day,
approximating military training
in the Arctic.
Since NAD+ is used by cells
to produce energy,
it's no surprise that we find
the primary NAD+
synthesizing enzyme
strongly upregulated
in tissues
that are actively inflamed.
For example,
the enzyme NAMPT is elevated
in colonoscopy biopsies
taken from inflamed areas
in patients with
inflammatory bowel disease,
and higher levels
are correlated
with greater disease severity.
So, for those suffering from
chronic autoimmune diseases,
such as rheumatoid arthritis,
NAD+ boosting
could potentially have
a "profound negative impact."
This explains
why tamping down NAD+
with NAMPT inhibitors
has been shown
to ameliorate colitis
and arthritis in mice,
but this has yet
to be tested in people.
Such NAD+ depleting drugs
have, however,
been used in cancer patients.
Malignancy is another heavily
energy-consuming process.
NAD+ may, therefore,
have a tumor-promoting effect
by promoting cancer cell growth
and spread.
For example, NAMPT,
the NAD+-forming enzyme,
is highly expressed
in cancerous brain tumors
and correlates with
decreased patient survival.
This has led to attempts
to use NAD+-depleting therapies
to try to starve
cancer progression,
but this approach is confounded
by rapid onset injury
to another
energy-intensive tissue,
the retina,
risking blindness.
Giving NMN to mice
with pancreatic cancer
accelerates the progression
of the cancer,
thought due to the aggravation
of inflammation.
The researchers conclude that
consumers of NAD+ supplements
must "balance the advantageous
anti-ageing effects
with the potential detrimental
pro-tumorigenic side effects."
Perhaps this explains
why the best NAD+ boosters
have ever been able to do
is increase mice lifespan
by five percent.
On the other hand,
as you'll remember,
NAM successfully prevented
human skin cancers
and has been found
to reduce the incidence
of a variety
of carcinogen-induced tumors
in rodents.
The disparate results
may in part be due
to the disparate impact
sirtuin activation
may have on different cancers.
Sirtuin activity
can be overexpressed
in some cancers
(like thyroid carcinomas
and lung metastasis)
but reduced in others
(like brain, bladder, prostate,
and ovarian tumors).
The bottom line
is that particular caution
should be used
for NAD+-boosting supplements
by those with cancer,
or a personal or strong
family history of cancer,
and perhaps also by those
with inflammatory disorders
and certain active infections.